NYSUT Field Services Department Files. 6174/004
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Field Services Department Files
1913-1999
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174/004
75 cubic feet
75 linear ft.
Articles, reports, pamphlets, correspondence.
5830503
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 13, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, November 04, 2014
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Biographical / Historical
NYSUT's Field and Legal Services Division provides direct services for members and locals through 16 regional offices, some 100 field representatives and a legal staff of 25 attorneys supported by approximately 50 administrative staff. It provides help with contract negotiation, enforcement of contract provisions by filing improper practice charges with the Public Employment Relations Board (PERB) or court system, representing teachers in tenure challenges or misconduct charges, providing strike assistance, and organizing new locals, including university faculty and non-teaching personnel. Extensive training programs on leadership skills and public relations were coordinated by the division. For many years, occupational safety and health was a major focus of the field service, especially important as many schools were found to need asbestos remediation. Internal accountability was tightly controlled; monthly activity reports were provided from each regional office, and expenditures were scrutinized in detail by the central office.
Initially, the field service function was organized around UniServ, which was set up by the National Education Association (NEA) in 1970 to place one full-time field representative in a region for each 1,200 NEA members. The NEA and its state affiliates funded UniServ. NEA local associations participated in the hiring of the UniServ representatives, and determined the role of the representatives in their regions.
After the merger with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT) in 1972, NYSUT reorganized its structure, and the UniServ program was replaced by a negotiated block grant payment from the NEA to NYSUT to pay for a portion of the costs of the field service program.
In 1972, Vito DeLeonardis became NYSUT's first Executive Director, and was responsible for field and legal services. Ken Law was the Director of Field Services. Robert Allen was the Assistant Director for Administration in Field Services and Daniel McKillip was Assistant Director for Operations in Field Services.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA, and lost some staff as a result. Dan McKillip and Ken Law left. Jim Conti became Assistant Director for Operations and Ray Ratte was Coordinator of Field Service Staff and Leadership Training. John O'Leary became Coordinator of Organizing in 1979.
The next major change in Field Services came in 1988 when Vito DeLeonardis retired and James Wood became the Executive Director. Robert Allen retired in 1998 and Pauline Kinsella replaced him as Director of Field Services. Jim Wood retired in 2003 as Executive Director and was replaced by Pauline Kinsella. In 2003, Mark Chaykin became Director of Field Operations.
Scope and Contents
Covers 1965-1999, with greatest focus in the 1970s and 1980s during Jim Conti's tenure as director of field services. Includes correspondence of Conti and of individual regional offices, activity reports and requests for legal assistance.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6174/004 AV: NYSUT Field Services Department Audio-Visual Material. All other 6174 collections
Teachers' unions -- New York (State); Allen, Robert; Chaykin, Mark; Conti, Jim; DeLeonardis, Vito; Kinsella, Pauline; Law, Ken; McKillip, Dan; O'Leary, John; Wood, James; New York State United Teachers, Field Services Department. Archives; New York State United Teachers. Archives; New York State United Teachers.
5830503
- Jim Conti Chronological File (1 of 3), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. January 2-June 17, 1986
- Jim Conti Chronological File (2 of 3), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. September 30-November 26, 1986
- Jim Conti Chronological File (3 of 3), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. July 1-September 30, 1986
- Jim Conti Chronological File (1 of 4), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. May 1-August 29, 1985
- Jim Conti Chronological File (2 of 4), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. February 14-April 30, 1985
- Jim Conti Chronological File (3 of 4), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. January 2-February 14, 1985
- Jim Conti Chronological File (4 of 4), 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. September 5-December 19, 1985
- Jim Conti Chronological File, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. October 31-December 20, 1984
- Legal, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Correspondence with the legal department re individual teachers; legal briefs; agreements; fact-finder's report for Mohonasen Central School District; items for negotiation for Broadalbin Teachers Association
- Albany: Lieberman, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Correspondence with Leon Lieberman, regional field coordinator
- Yorktown Congress of Teachers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Elmsford: Klein, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Correspondence re East Ramapo Teachers Association referendum re affiliation with NEA or AFT
- Jericho(Nassau Count): O'Leary, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Correspondence re affiliation dispute of Nassau Community College Adjunct Faculty Association; memo from John O'Leary, head of Jericho office, asking urgently for more field representatives; other issues re Nassau Regional Office
- Mid: Hudson-Kern, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Public Employment Relations Board improper practice charges, brought by Red Hook Faculty Association, Onteora Non-Teaching Employees Association; NYS Department of Labor decision in unemployment case
- New York City: Ficcio/Federation of Catholic Teachers, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Memo re Federation of Catholic Teachers organizing campaign; correspondence re tensions between FCT and NYSUT field representatives; preliminary report, "Prospects for Organizing the Research Foundation of the State University of New York"; memo re results of affiliation election at Albert Einstein College of Medicine
- Potsdam: Allen, RJ (North Country) Chron File, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Correspondence re Alexandria Bay vote to disaffiliate with NYSUT and affiliate with NYEA; Public Employment Relations Board decision in Gouverneur Central School District case; grievances re individual teachers
- Rochester Regional Office, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Faculty representative handbook; materials re affiliation vote; Rochester Teachers Association Executive Council meeting minutes; activity reports; newsletters by NYSUT and by NYEA/NEA; Public Employment Relations Board improper practice charge; legal briefs
- Southern Tier Regional Office, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Arbitration case re back pay, Candor Teachers Association and Candor Central School; Public Employment Relations Board decision re Whitney Point Central School District and Whitney Point Teachers Association; legal brief re Horseheads Central School District and Horseheads Teachers Association; agreement between New Berlin Central School and New Berlin Faculty Association; monthly reports; correspondence
- Hauppauge (Suffolk): DeGregorio, John F., 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Correspondence
- Syracuse (Liverpool): Squillace, Frank, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Consent agreement for representation election between Teachers United of Sandy Creek and Sandy Creek Teachers Association; memos to staff from Frank Squillace; 1978-79 operations report; activities reports
- Syracuse Regional Office, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Arbitration brief re longevity increment grievance, Tully Teachers Association and Tully Central School District; correspondence
- Utica: Grove, Vincent, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Public Employment Relations Board improper practice charges, brought by Westmoreland Teachers Association; exceptions to Public Employment Relations Board decision by Whitesboro Teachers Association; legal advice re self-insurance by school districts
- Buffalo Western Regional Office: Uba, Ron, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Statement of charges against individual tenured teacher by Board of Education of Lockport City School District re misconduct, insubordination and incompetence; correspondence re affiliation elections in Jamestown and Wellsville
- Jim Conti Chronological File (1 of3), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. January-April, 1979
- Jim Conti Chronological File (2 of3), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. May-September, 1979
- Jim Conti Chronological File (3 of3), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Outgoing correspondence from director of field services. October-December, 1979. Includes date book
- Jim Conti BOCES Conference, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  November 15, 1979. Newsletters; BOCES conference program; Labor-Management Reporting and Disclosure Act Interpretive Bulletin; agenda for Coordinators' Meeting; draft Report of Coordinators Committee; list of locals in arrears as of October 9, 1979; Report on the 58th Representative Assembly of the National Education Association, July 2-5, 1979, prepared for officers and staff of the American Federation of Teachers by director of field communications; transcript of Secretary-Treasurer Lane Kirkland's Press Conference, Executive Council meeting; whit paper, The UAW Reaffiliation with the AFL-CIO; letter re sexual misconduct hearing of individual teacher; supplement to the 1978 Policy Handbook
- Board of Directors Meeting, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  December 7, 1979. Agenda; summary of actions taken at December 7-8, 1979, meeting; proposed resolution on Board of Regents Recommendation on Corporal Punishment; interim policy statement on State Education Department's proposal to redesign business education in New York State; proposed position paper on registration of secondary schools; resolution for Public Employees Federation affiliation and agreement; balance sheets; proposed regulations for children with handicapping conditions; Regents recommendations on teaching as a profession and teacher competence
- Executive Committee meeting, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  December 5, 1979, La Guardia Terminal. Agenda; Regents proposals; legal services invoice and related correspondence re Nassau Community College Federation of Teachers strike; monthly membership report
- Coordinator's Meeting, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  May 24, 1979. Agenda; materials for performance appraisal interview workshop; articles and newsletters
- Coordinator's Meeting/Board Meeting, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  August 29, 1979. Agenda; activity report; newsletters and articles
- Coordinator's Meeting/PSA/CWA/Strike Info, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  PSA (Professional Staff Association) Strike News Update; confidential memos
- Jim Conti Confidential, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  New York State Comparative Salary Data; "The Condition of Education, 1979 Edition," statistical report, National Center for Education Statistics, U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare; collective bargaining agreement, NYSUT and Communication Workers of America, Local 1141
- Jim Conti: Coordinators Meeting, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  October 17, 1979. Coordinators' meeting agenda; report of coordinators committee; recap of impasses; newspaper clipping
- Health Care Organizing/UFT/NYSUT, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Guides for organizers re National Labor Relations Act, organizing and leading volunteers, health manpower (types of health care workers); article reprints; newsletters and other printed materials
- Organizing Expense Invoices, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Organizing Nurses Rochester: Expense Invoices (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Organizing Nurses, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Fact sheet Q&A by NYSUT; by-laws and extracts from articles of incorporation, New York State Nurses Association; statistics re nurses salaries
- Organizing Nurses Rochester: Paul Luczak, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Nurse Organizing Rochester, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Nurses Convention Syracuse, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Organizing materials
- Organizing: Paul Doyle, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Document, "Prospects for Organizing the Research Foundation of the State University of New York"
- Elmsford Regional Office, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Results of Arden Hills Hospital vote
- Jericho Regional Office, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- New York City Regional Office, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- North Country Regional Office, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Rochester Regional Office, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Activity reports and related correspondence re organizing activities
- Suffolk Regional Office, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Syracuse Regional Office, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Vestal Regional Service Center, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Activity and planning reports
- Western Regional Office, 1967-1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Jim Conti: Ithaca College, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  Document, "Profiles of the Ithaca College Faculty Association Bargaining Election"; National Labor Relations Board correspondence; President Whalen's Comments to the Faculty Meeting, December 6, 1977; organizing leaflets and related materials; American Association of University Professors (AAUP) brief to NLRB
- VOTE/COPE Campaign: Info Training Manuals, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  Information & Training Manual, Committee on Political Education of NYSUT, 1974; Politics, 1980; COPE Manual: A Political Action Guide, 1981
- Legislative Report, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  1979 United Teachers Legislative Program; NYSUT Major Legislative Gains, '74-'78; VOTE/COPE contribution list as of July 31, 1979
- Local President's Guide, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Division of Research & Educational Services Local Presidents' Guide; Local Leaders' Guide; Leaders' Handbook for Building an Effective Organization
- Facts and Figures, 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  NYSUT reports for local presidents to assist in persuading teachers to affiliate
- Florida Education Association: Collective Bargaining Manuals, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  "Strategies and Methods of Presenting the Salary and Fringe Package"; "Use and Abuse of Impasse Procedures"; text of Florida Public Employee Collective Bargaining Law
- Arbitrator Training Material, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Brochures and seminar outline by American Arbitration Association, National Center for Dispute Settlement, and NYSUT
- Professional Workers and Unionization: A data Handbook, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Prepared for Department for Professional Employees, Authored By AFL-CIO
- AFT Strike Preparedness Booklet, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- National Conference for Teacher Unity Meetings, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Meeting minutes; financial statement
- National Public Employer Labor Relations: Maintaining public services: Strike Planning Manual, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Document, "Maintaining Public Services: The NPELRA Strike Planning Manual," part 1
- National Public Employer Labor Relations: Strike Manual Part 2: Legal remedies available to a public employer in the event of an Illegal Strike, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  "Legal Remedies Available to a Public Employer in the Event of an Illegal Strike"
- Union Representative's Guide to NLRB RC and CA cases, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  "A Survival Kit for Union Representatives Exploring the Mysterious Regions of the National Labor Relations Board," a Policy & Practice publication by Center for Labor Research and Education, Institute of Industrial Relations, University of California, Los Angeles
- Urban Executive Secretary: Loan Kit. NEA, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Material collected from NEA chapters re how to employ an executive secretary, duties
- Proposal to Establish the Career Development Network of the SUNY Community Colleges, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Proposal submitted to New York State Department of Labor by Office of Community Colleges, SUNY
- NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services: Community College Data, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Data Relative to NYS Community Colleges under SUNY Jurisdiction, Budgeted Revenues and Expenditures for 1978-79, September 1979; Revenues & Expenditures for 1977-78; 1977-78 Teacher Contract Analysis summary, September 1978
- Reports: SEIU, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  "A Decade of Progress: 3,000 Victories 300,000 Workers," 1980 Convention Organizing Report; "So Much to Be Done: George Hardy's Life in Organized Labor"
- Reports, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  Public School Professional Personnel Report: New York State 1978-79, State Education Department; 1970 New York State Teachers Association Annual Report of the Executive Secretary
- Reports: State Education Department, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  Report of the Subcommittee on Per Diem Substitute Teachers, 1981; Minimum Requirements for Schools in New York State, 1980
- AFT Convention Report, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Contract Negotiations: United University Professionals, State of New York, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Proposals by United University Professors; proposals by State of New York
- CWA Contract, PSA Grievance, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Agreement between NYSUT and Local 1141 Communication Workers of America, AFL- CIO; Professional Staff Association grievances over maternity leave, sick time
- NEA "For the Record" Press Clippings, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  Bound collection of nationwide news clippings re NYSUT, AFT, AAUP, and other organizations considered unfriendly to or competing with the National Education Association, complied by NEA and annotated to highlight negative items
- New York Educators Association (NYEA/NEA) Materials, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  Membership Chairperson's Handbook; Public Relations Chairperson's Handbook; Year-End Legislative Report and NEA Position Papers, August 1976; You Count, Schools Count, Legal Defense Counts publicity brochures; related materials
- NYEA: United Teachers Board Objections/Ex list, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  Letter from Public Employment Relations Board that petition for certification/decertification had been filed by United Teachers of Buffalo and NYSUT; letter from trial examiner John Crotty to NYEA attorney that Buffalo Teachers Federation might raise allegations of fraud re United Teachers of Buffalo; preliminary list of objections
- NEA: Uniserv, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- NEA Governance and Committee Directory, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- NYSUT Constitution, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Teaching as a Profession, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Reports by State Education Department
- Campaign Fayetteville: Manlius-Confidential, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Warsaw Teachers Campaign (NYSUT V. NEA/NYEA), 1978 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- NYSUT Budget Workshop: Confidential, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Prepared by Office of Secretary-Treasurer
- NYSUT Miscellaneous, 1970-1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Schedule of NYSUT Employees and Other Personnel, 9/1/79 8/31/80; resume of Jim Conti; resume of Diane Wagner; memo re expenditures during strike, December 8, 1972; legal opinion on employer payment of employees' Social Security contributions, March 5, 1970; Judge Dillon' Remarks TRO Hearing for Niagara-Orleans BOCES, November 6, 1975; program for joint Board of Directors/managers meeting, "Education: The Next Decade: NYSUT Program for the 80s," August 24-26, 1979; NYSUT management financial report printout, July 1979; George Meany commemorative first-day issue cancelled stamp; personal correspondence
- United University Professions Campaign (1 of 2), 1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Membership lists; correspondence; constitution and bylaws; publicity materials
- United University Campaign (2 of 2), 1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- A. Anderson United University Professions Campaign, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Harris survey, "A Follow-Up Study of the Attitudes of the SUNY Staff Toward Collective Bargaining and UUP Representation," September 1978; original survey, conducted for NYSUT/UUP, June 1978; memo from campaign coordinator Tony Anderson re guidelines for collective bargaining assistance to chapters; correspondence re NEA activities, strategy
- Coordinator's Meeting Minutes, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Monthly summaries of Executive Director's Report, Legislative Report, Secretary-Treasurer's Report, Research & Educational Services Report, President's Report, NYEA activities, coordinators' reports from various regional districts, other matters
- Coordinator's Meeting Minutes, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Coordinator's Meeting Minutes, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Coordinator's Meeting Minutes, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Coordinator's Meeting Minutes, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Vito Deleonardis Chronological File, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Incoming and outgoing correspondence from NYSUT Executive Director Vito DeLeonardis re interviews for field representative, grievances, intern and field staff training, request for additional secretarial support
- Vito Deleonardis Chronological File, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Incoming and outgoing correspondence from NYSUT Executive Director Vito DeLeonardis
- Vito Deleonardis Chronological File, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 13)